It's always welcome back to JupyterLab, my favorite place to be.
유피터랩은 언제나 환영이죠 제가 제일 좋아하는 곳이에요
And now we are, of course in the week five folder.
지금은 5주 차 폴더에 있죠
And I'm looking here at the day one Jupyter notebook in week five, which is going to be our home for
이건 5주 차에 작성된 첫째 날 주피터 노트예요 오늘 우리가 지낼 곳이죠 아주
today, where we look at building our own DIY rag implementation in a very simplistic way, but it will
단순한 방식으로 DIY 래그 구현을 구축할 겁니다 하지만 이게 어떻게 작동하는지
give you some real insight into how this works.
통찰력을 줄 거예요
So first of all, let me tell you about our company in Shoreham, an insurance tech company.
우선 쇼어햄에 있는 우리 보험 기술 회사에 대해 말씀드리죠
We have got access to their company shared folder and it's called Knowledge Base and I have dropped
회사 공유 폴더에 엑세스 권한이 있어요 노웨어 베이스라는 거죠 같은 주에 여기 5개
it right here in the same week five folder for your perusal.
폴더에 넣어뒀어요 여러분이 정독하세요
If we open it up, you'll see that it contains four folders company contracts, employees and products
열어보면 4개의 폴더가 있어요 회사 계약서, 직원과 제품 4개의
representing four different um divisions or four different areas of the company.
다른 부서나 4개의 분야를 나타내는 것들이죠
Um, now, one thing I will mention, as you may have guessed perhaps, is that you'll see a fair amount
한 가지 언급할 것은 이미 짐작하셨겠지만 여기 회사 데이터가 꽤 많이
of company data here, which is all completely fictitious.
있습니다 전부 완전히 허구예요
This was, of course created by an LLM.
이건 LLM이 만든 거예요
I took took my own exercise from a couple of weeks ago, wrote a data generator and used it to craft
몇 주 전에 했던 운동을 그대로 하면서 데이터 생성기를 작성해서 데이터 일부를 만드는 데 사용했어요
some of this data and keep relationships between some of the documents and so on.
몇몇 문서와 기타 등등의 관계를 유지하기 위해서요
I did add in a little couple of tweaks here and there myself, but almost all of this is generated by
저도 몇 가지 수정을 추가하긴 했지만 거의 모든 것은
either GPT four or by Claude.
GPT 4나 클로드가 생성했어요
So just to have a quick peek at this in company, there's a few things here about the company.
회사에서 이걸 잠깐 보죠 회사에 관한 게 몇 가지 있어요
I think these are quite short documents if these are in the form of markdown documents.
마크다운 문서라면 꽤 짧은 문서라고 생각해요
So if I can open it in this way, then we get to see some nice, um, write ups about the insurer Elm.
이렇게 열 수 있으면 INurer Elmlm에 대한 평가서를 볼 수 있어요
It was founded apparently by Avery Lancaster in 2015.
2015년에 에이버리 랭커스터가 설립한 것으로 알려져 있죠
Remember, Avery's name will be.
에이버리 이름을 쓸 거예요
We'll be meeting her a few times.
몇 번 만날 거예요
Um, and if you want to see the original documents, of course.
원본 문서도 보여 드릴게요
They look like the markdown that we are familiar with.
우리가 잘 아는 마크다운처럼 보여요
Um, then if we go back into knowledge base in contracts.
그럼 계약의 지식 기반으로 돌아가 보죠
We've got some more substantive information about contracts, which includes the contract terms renewal,
계약에 관해 보다 실질적인 정보를 얻었는데요 계약 조건 갱신과 계약에 포함된
the features that are included in that contract that's going to come back and be important later.
기능은 나중에 중요하게 다루게 될 텐데요
So so keep note of that.
그러니 기억해 두세요
Um, and some other things.
다른 것들도요
Uh, if we go back into knowledge base again and look at employees, these are the employee HR records
다시 지식 기반으로 돌아가서 직원들을 살펴보면 이건 다양한 직원들의 직원 인사
of the different employees.
기록이에요
And even the CEO, Avery Lancaster herself has an HR record that you'll see right here.
CEO인 에이버리 랭커스터도 인사팀의 기록이 있어요
Uh, so all everyone has their their HR documents, um, and then products contains a write up of the
모두 인사 서류를 갖고 있고 제품에는 인큐어 엘름에서 제안한 다양한
different offerings from insurer Elm, including car Elm, uh, for auto insurance, uh home Elm and
공지 사항이 적혀 있어요 자동차 보험에 대한 카 엘름도 있고 홈 엘름 등도 있죠
You can look through these documents, but they are wonderful in how real they are.
이 문서들을 훑어보면 정말 사실적이라는 게 놀라워요
All of course courtesy of Frontier Models.
프론티어 모델스 협찬이죠
A nice product summary right there with even with a roadmap.
로드맵을 가지고도 훌륭한 제품 요약이에요
Love it.
좋아요
Uh, okay.
네
Back then to day one.
그 시절 첫날부터요
So what are we going to do?
그럼 어떻게 하죠?
We are going to write something now that is going to be asking questions about this company, and we
이 회사에 대한 질문을 하는 뭔가를 지금 작성하겠습니다 인위적으로
are going to artificially look up and insert context into the prompt.
찾아보고 프롬프트에 컨텍스트를 삽입하는 거죠
So we do some imports.
수입도 좀 하고요
We're going to use GPT four mini this time.
이번에는 GPT 4 미니를 사용할 거예요
Um, and um uh, so now we get to the juice.
이제 주스 얘기를 해보죠 get it get it
So what we do here this this is a Python function which will, uh, look in this folder and take all
그래서 여기서 하는 건 이건 Python 함수입니다 이 폴더 안에서 모든 콘텐츠를
of its contents and put it into a list.
취해 리스트에 넣는 거죠
Employees.
직원들요
So employees is, in fact, now going to be a list of the file names in knowledge base slash employees.
따라서 직원은 이제 지식 기반/직원 파일명 목록이 되겠죠
And for each one, this is some janky code that that is just sort of hacked together, which basically
각각의 파일은 엉성한 코드인데 해킹을 당해서 파일의 이름을 취해요
takes the name of the file, which is in fact an employee's Floyd's name and takes the their last name.
사실 직원의 플로이드 이름인데 거기에 성을 취하죠
It just splits out their last name opens up that file and puts it into a dictionary where the key is
성을 분할해 파일을 열고 사전에 넣죠 키는 직원 이름이고
the employee name and the document is the document.
문서는 문서예요
So let's just run this if we have a look at this.
이걸 실행해 보죠 이걸 보세요
So we're expecting to see a dictionary.
사전이 나올 거라고 기대해요
Uh sorry.
미안해요
Um let's see it's called context or dictionary.
문맥이나 사전이라고 하죠
Let's just look at all of the keys in context.
모든 키를 문맥 안에서 살펴보죠
So here are the keys.
여기 열쇠요
The keys are indeed the last names of the employees, as you would expect.
예상하셨겠지만 열쇠는 직원들의 성이에요
And one of them is Lancaster, our CEO.
그중 한 명은 CEO인 랭커스터예요
So let's just have a quick look at Lancaster.
랭커스터를 간단히 살펴보죠
So we should simply be able to look in our dictionary at Lancaster.
랭커스터 사전에서 간단히 찾아볼 수 있죠
And we should just see bam the markdown document from her HR record.
뱀이 인사 기록에서 하락 문서를 떼는 걸 봐야 해요
Nothing magic at all going on here, reading in files, shoving them in a dictionary.
마법 같은 일은 전혀 없어요 파일을 읽고 사전에 쑤셔 넣는 거요
That's all there is to it.
그게 다예요
So now let's just extend this And what we're going to do here is do exactly the same thing for the products.
이제 이걸 확장해보죠 여기서 하려는 건 제품에 대해 정확히 같은 걸 하는 거예요
Look in the products folder, iterate through each of the files, pluck out its name, and then shove
제품 폴더를 보세요, 각각의 파일을 반복해 이름을 빼내고 같은 컨텍스트
that in the same context dictionary.
사전에 밀어 넣어요
So now if I look in the if I run that first, try not to forget that.
이제 보면∙∙∙ 먼저 실행하면∙∙∙ 잊지 않도록 하세요
There we go.
됐어요
And now look at the keys.
이제 건반을 보세요
We should see a combination of employee last names and product names.
직원들의 성과 제품명을 조합한 게 보일 거예요
Here are the last names and their market.
이게 그 회사 성이랑 시장이에요
L'm home.
다녀왔어요
L'm calm.
진정했어요
Are the product names okay?
제품명은 괜찮아요?
Ready for action.
준비됐죠?
We'll have a system message.
시스템 메시지예요
You are an expert in answering accurate questions about ensure l'm the insurance tech company.
보험 회사인지 아닌지 묻는 질문에 정확하게 대답하는 전문가죠
Give brief, accurate answers.
간결하고 정확하게 대답하세요
If you don't know the answer, say so.
모르면 모른다고 하세요
Do not make anything up.
지어내지 마세요
If you haven't been provided with relevant context.
관련 맥락을 제공받지 못했다면요
It turns out that making these kinds of very authoritative instructions in the system prompt to tell
매우 신뢰할 만한 설명을 시스템에 입력하면 아무것도 발명하지 말라고
the model not to invent things is effective in stopping it from hallucinating and keeping accuracy high.
경고하는 효과가 있어서 환각 증상을 막고 정확도를 높일 수 있죠
We're going to see that again later, too, but it's worth bearing in mind in keeping this one in your
나중에 다시 살펴보겠지만 기억해두실 가치가 있어요 이걸 여러분 노트북에
in your notebook or in a list of useful things, because that kind of prompting is useful when accuracy
두시거나 유용한 것 목록에 두시길 바랍니다 정확성이 필수적일 땐 프롬프트도 유용하거든요
So we will see that we will add that in to get we will make a function called get relevant context.
그걸 추가해 관련 컨텍스트 get이라는 함수를 만들 거예요
So what this function is going to do this is very important.
이 함수가 하는 일은 아주 중요해요
It's going to um uh it's going to take um a message, any kind of message.
이건 메시지가 될 거예요 어떤 종류의 메시지든요
Uh, and it's then going to iterate through the context, taking the title and the details out of each
컨텍스트를 반복할 거예요 컨텍스트에 있는 각각의 아이템에서 제목과 세부 사항을
item in the context.
가져오는 거죠
And it's going to see whether or not the title, the, the, either the last name of the employee or
그리고 타이틀인지 아닌지 직원의 성인지 제품인지를 봅니다
the product name, if it's a product, if that exists anywhere in the message.
제품이라면요 메시지 어딘가에 있다면요
If that text, like the word Lancaster, is anywhere in the message, then it's simply going to shove
랭커스터라는 단어가 메시지의 어디에 있든 간에 이 관련 컨텍스트 리스트에
that into this list of relevant context and return that list in the end.
밀어넣을 것입니다 그리고 리스트를 반환하죠
So let me show you exactly what that means.
그게 무슨 뜻인지 보여드리죠
So if I say get relevant context and I pass in something completely irrelevant, like the cat, we'll
관련 컨텍스트를 get 하고 완전히 무관한 걸 넘긴다면 고양이 같은 거요 아무것도 못 얻어요
The cat is not relevant to the questions about ensure.
고양이는 보장 문제와 관련이 없어요
And if I put who is Avery Lancaster then hooray!
그래서 에이버리 랭커스터가 누구인지를 입력하면, 만세! Tipet up! Tipet up! Tipet up! Tipet up! Tipet up! Tipet up!
We will in fact get a good robust, uh, answer in there, which is exactly what we would expect.
사실 아주 확실한 답이 나올 겁니다 우리가 기대하는 바로 그 답이죠 get it get it get it
If I say, who is Avery Lancaster and what is calm, then we should hopefully let's have a look.
에이버리 랭커스터가 누구고 누가 차분한지 물으면 한번 보죠
See that we'll get back a list of two things that will include.
포함할 수 있는 두 가지 목록이 get을 받게 되죠
Yes, you can see there's the second one beginning.
네, 두 번째가 시작되는 게 보이시죠
That's column in there.
저게 기둥이에요
We get back a list that contains Avery's document and the column document.
에이버리의 문서와 열 문서가 담긴 목록을 받았죠 get it get it
Um, but of course this is very brittle.
물론 아주 잘 부서지죠
If I don't include Avery's last name, I just say Avery and I spell this without a capital C because
Avery 성을 빼고 Avery라고만 쓸게요 대문자 C 없이요 대소문자 구분이
I haven't even done a case insensitive match there.
안 되는 매치도 아직 안 했거든요
We're going to discover we get nothing back.
Get을 해도 얻는 게 없다는 걸 알게 되겠죠
This is brittle.
잘 부서져요
It's only going to work in basic cases.
기본 케이스에만 적용될 거예요
All right, so now I just build on this one step further by having a function add context that takes
이제 한 단계 더 나아가서 함수 추가 컨텍스트를 만들어 메시지를
a message.
받죠
Um, so the idea is that this will simply get any relevant context.
간단히 어떤 관련 컨텍스트든 get이 되는 거죠
And if it finds some it's going to add that into the message.
뭔가를 찾으면 그걸 메시지에 추가하죠
It's going to say the following additional context might be relevant in answering this question.
다음의 추가적인 컨텍스트가 이 질문에 대답하는 데 관련 있을 수 있다고 할 거예요
So it's just sort of building on top of whatever it's passed.
지나간 것 위에 뭔가를 쌓는 거예요
So to give an example Let's just ask again the question.
예를 들어보죠 질문을 다시 해보죠
Um, but yeah, let me start with who is Avery Lancaster, a positive example, and I'll give you a
에이버리 랭커스터부터 시작할게요 긍정적인 예죠 나쁜 예도
bad example.
있어요
Who is Avery Lancaster and what, you have to run the cell.
에이버리 랭커스터가 누구고 감방을 운영해야 한다고요
Uh, so, uh, who is Avery Lancaster?
에이버리 랭커스터가 누구죠?
What do we see?
뭐가 보이죠?
Uh, we see.
그렇군요
Here we go.
시작할게요
Uh, who is Avery Lancaster?
에이버리 랭커스터가 누구죠?
The following additional context might be relevant in answering this question.
다음의 추가적인 맥락은 이 질문에 대답하는 데 관련이 있을 수 있죠
And then there is the detail.
세세한 부분까지 신경 써야 해요
Uh, and then I can give a counter example.
제가 반대 예시를 들어볼게요
Another kind of problem.
또 다른 문제요
If I say who is Alex Lancaster, it will still see the word Lancaster in there.
알렉스 랭커스터가 누구냐고 물으면 랭커스터라고 쓰여 있을 거예요
And of course, it's still going to say here is relevant context.
물론 여전히 관련 컨텍스트라고 하죠
Um, and it's of course missed the trick there.
물론 거기서 묘기를 놓쳤죠
So it is rough and ready.
그래서 조잡해요
Um, it really is just doing a string lookup.
문자열만 살펴보는 거예요
But that's all we need, of course, to be writing our favorite chat function.
하지만 최애 채팅 함수를 쓰려면 그 정도면 충분하죠
You remember, this is the function that Gradio expects.
이게 그라디오가 기대하는 함수라는 걸 기억하세요
If it's to build a quick user interface, it takes the current message and the history of messages,
사용자 인터페이스를 빠르게 만들려면 현재 메시지와 메시지의 이력을 취해야 합니다
and we hopefully this is now second nature to you.
이제 이게 여러분께 제2의 본성이 됐으면 좋겠네요
We convert that history into the format that OpenAI expects, the list of dicts in that particular structure.
히스토리를 OpenAI가 기대하는 형식으로 변환합니다 특정 구조의 독재 목록이죠
And then we make this lovely call here.
그리고 이 멋진 전화를 걸죠
We added extra context to our message, and that's what we send to OpenAI.
메시지에 컨텍스트를 추가해 오픈AI에 보냈어요
And then this of course OpenAI chat completions create also second nature to you and we will stream
오픈AI 채팅 완료 역시 여러분께 제2의 본성이 되어 응답을 스트림으로
back the response.
보내드리죠
So let's give this a run.
실행해 보죠
And now we know the last step is the one liner that brings this up in Gradio.
이제 마지막 단계는 그래디오에서 이걸 불러오는 한 줄 대사예요
Here we go.
시작할게요
Let's see how this looks.
어떤지 보죠
So let's say, uh.
이렇게 말해 보죠
Hi there.
안녕하세요
How can I assist you today?
무엇을 도와드릴까요?
So we'll say, who is Avery Lancaster?
에이버리 랭커스터가 누구냐고 물어보죠
That's right.
맞아요
Yeah.
네
Lancaster.
랭커스터요
And of course, we get back a nice good answer because we know full well that the Avery Lancaster information
물론 좋은 답변이 나왔죠 에이버리 랭커스터 정보가 입력된 정보를 오픈라이에 보냈다는 걸 알고
was shoved into the prompt and sent to OpenAI.
있었으니까요 get it
Um, and now we can also say what is calm.
이제 뭐가 평온한지 말해 볼까요?
And innovative auto insurance product.
혁신적인 자동차 보험 상품도 있죠
And there we go.
다 됐어요
It's got a whole ton of information summarized from that big chunk of context that will have centered
제품에 대해 중점을 두고 있는 큰 컨텍스트에서 요약되는 정보가 엄청나게
about the product.
많아요
And it even mentions the roadmap for continuous improvement.
로드맵을 통해 계속 개선할 수 있다고도 하죠
Lovely.
좋아요
Uh, so you can see it's rag.
누더기인 거 보이시죠?
It's simplistic, but, you know, this is what it's all about.
단순하지만 이게 바로 핵심이에요
Let's just break it for a second.
잠깐 끊고 얘기하죠
You can imagine what I'm going to do.
내가 뭘 할지 알죠?
I'm just going to say, uh, who is Avery?
에이버리가 누군지 물어볼게요
Well, it may it actually has the the conversation from the past, so we should probably start this
사실 예전에 했던 대화가 들어 있어요 다시 시작해야겠네요
Bring up a fresh chat.
새로운 대화를 해요
Otherwise it will know who Avery it is because we just asked it before and it got the context.
안 그러면 에이버리가 누군지 알 거예요 아까 물어봤잖아요
So let's bring up a fresh new user interface and try it from scratch and not give it that benefit and
새로운 사용자 인터페이스를 가져와서 처음부터 시도해보죠 그런 장점은 주지 말고 그냥 물어보세요
Who is Avery?
에이버리가 누구죠?
I'm sorry, but I don't have any information about Avery in relation to ensure.
죄송하지만 에이버리에 대한 정보가 없어요
So you can see that it's brittle.
잘 부러지는 게 보이죠?
It has to take the last name.
성을 따야 해요
And even if I spell the last name wrong, who is Lancaster without, uh, a capital L, it's also going
성 철자를 틀려도 대문자 L이 없는 랭커스터는 망가지기 마련이니 이해하시죠?
to break, so you get the idea.
Get it
This is an effective way to add supplemental information into the prompt.
추가 정보를 추가하는 효과적인 방법이죠
It gets back more accurate answers, but it is brittle and it requires exact text matching.
더 정확한 답을 얻지만 글자가 정확히 일치해야 해요
Not particularly flexible, not very scalable solution.
유연하지도 확장성도 낮은 해결책이죠
Uh, we can do better.
더 잘할 수 있어요
And that is what we are going to be doing in the in the next day.
내일 우리가 할 일이 바로 그거예요
But now back to the slides.
이제 슬라이드로 돌아가죠